\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-081 Assignment 1

Overview

The purposes of this assignment are to familiarize you with the use of the laboratory facilities for the course and to establish standard procedures for developing web projects for the course.

Procedure

Log into your account and verify that it is working correctly.

Log into any one of the computers in A-205 or A-227 using your account name for this course, which consists of the first letter of your first name, your last name, and the digits “081” all as a single lower-case string. That is, if your name is "Always A. Good Student", your account name is astudent081. Use the password given to you in class, and remember that you will be required to change it to something secure the first time you log in.

The names of the computers are:

A-205 | A-227
birch | apple
cherry | fir
chestnut | juniper
elm | mimosa
ginkgo | peach
hemlock | pine
hickory | plum
  | spruce
  | sycamore
  | walnut

Room 205 is an “open lab,” which means you can use them any time you want. The secretaries in the CS Department Office (A-202) will open the lab for you if it is closed. Room 227 is a closed lab, so you will not be able to sit at the computers in that room to use them. However, all of the computers are accessible from the Internet. If you have access to a computer running Windows XP with a broadband connection, you can use Remote Desktop to log in. From the Start button, go to Programs, to Accessories, to Communications, and you will find it. When it asks you what computer you want to connect to, pick one of the names above and add the domain name “.cs.qc.edu” to the computer name. For example, you would log into ginkgo by entering ginkgo.cs.qc.edu.

When you use Remote Desktop, select one of the computers in A-227 so that students who are on campus will be able to use the computers in A-205. The exception to this rule is from 5:00 to 6:15pm on Tuesdays and Thursdays, when there is a class using room A-227.

Use Windows Explorer to verify that your “My Documents” directory contains a directory named “My Web Pages.” That directory should already contain a file named template.xhtml, which you will be using as a starting point for the web pages you write for this course.

Make a copy of template.xhtml named index.xhtml in the same directory.

Log off the computer you used and log into another one.

On the second computer, verify that your index.xhtml file shows up in your My Web Pages directory, indicating that your “profile” (settings) were successfully copied to the domain server (maple) when you logged off the first computer and that they were then copied to the second computer when you logged into it. If you have any problems with this step, contact Dr. Vickery for help before proceeding with the remainder of the assignment.

Edit index.xhtml and test it.

Use any text editor to change the title and h1 elements of your index.xhtml file from the word “Template” to your own name. It would be best to use a programming editor such as Vim, or even the full web IDE, Dreamweaver. However, it is possible to make the change using Notepad, but you have to put quotation marks around the file name when you save it or Notepad will change the name to a index.xhtml.txt, and the web server won’t be able to display it properly because of the wrong extension.

Here are links to some introductory material on the programming editors available to you in this course:

Using Vim
Using Dreamweaver

There are four ways you can try to view your new index.xhtml web page in a browser, but only three of them will work!

(This is the technique that does not work!) Click on the file using Windows Explorer. Windows recognizes that .xhtml files are web pages and tells the default browser to show the page. But our template file includes some server-side scripting code written in PHP, and its presence will confuse the browser, which will display a cryptic error message.
Start Firefox, and type the URL “localhost/~astudent081” into the location bar, substituting your own account name for astudent081.
This technique is the same as the previous one, but substitute the name of the computer you are using for the word “localhost” in the URL.
This technique is the same as the previous one, but enter the Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) for the name of the computer you are using. The proper FQDN for the computers in the lab is the name of the computer name followed by “.cs.qc.cuny.edu” (ginkgo.cs.qc.cuny.edu, for example), but you can safely leave out the “.cuny” part if you want to.

Note that only the last technique will work for accessing your web page from another computer, and even that technique will only work while you are logged into the computer whose FQDN you use.

Now copy (don’t move) your web page from your “My Web Pages” directory to C:\htdocs and verify that you can view it by specifying just the computer name in the address bar.

Submit the Assignment

When you have completed the assignment, send me an email message that says “CS-081 Assignment 1” in the subject line and that contains your real name and account name in the message body. I will get a copy of your work from maple to look at.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-081 Assignment 3

Overview

For this assignment, you are to use a stylesheet and an image to customize the look of your course home page.

Procedure

Get rid of the JavaScript alert.

Edit your template.js file, and remove the alert() statement. This assignment does not use any JavaScript.

Make sure your Firefox extensions are up to date.

Start Firefox, select Tools→Extensions, and click the Find Updates button. Click any Update Now buttons, close the Extensions panel, exit Firefox, and start it up again.

Use Firebug to examine the current structure of your home page.

At this point, your home page consists of header, content, and footer divs. The only thing in the header is a h1 tag, and the only thing in the content is a h2 tag. View your home page in Firefox, and open up the Firebug extension. You can do this any of three ways: press F12, click on the smaller green circle with a checkmark in it at the bottom of the browser window, or use the Tools→Firebug menu.

Select the Inspect tab in the Firebug panel, and open up the DOM tree view so you can see both the head and content div tags and the heading tags inside them. Hover over the all four elements, observe the outline boxes in the page itself, and verify that the headings occupy exactly the same space on the web page as the div elements that contain them. We will start updating the page by adding some space below the headings so you can add some formatting to the divisions that won’t be covered up by the headings.

Unfortunately, to do this you need to use code based on topics covered in Chapter 11, which has not officially been assigned yet. Here is what you need to add to your screen.css file:

Sample Code

h1, h2 {
  padding:          0 0 0.5em 0.5em;
  }

#header, #content {
  padding:          0.5em 0 0.5em 0;
  }
            

Briefly, what you are doing here is adding a half em of space on the bottom and the left of each heading, and a half em of space to the top and bottom of the two divs. Use Firebug to verify that there is space between the headings and the divs that contain them.

Add some dummy content.

To evaluate the visual effects that you are going to add, it will help to have more of a page to work with. Use a common technique for adding ummy text to a web page: go to Lorem Ipsum and have it generate five paragraphs of Latin text for you. Just click the “Generate Lorem Ipsum” button, and paste the paragraphs into your web page right under the h2 element in the content div. Surround each paragraph with p and /p tags, and adjust the formatting of the source code to maintain proper indentation if necessary. Add another h2 element between the second and third paragraphs that you just entered. Use Lorem Ipsum again to generate a few words for the content of the new heading, and again to change the content of the original h2 element. View the web page to make sure it looks right.

Apply different background colors to headings and paragraphs.

Add three css rules to screen.css, one each for h1, h2, and p tags. Select a harmonious set of three color for the backgrounds of these three sets of elements. Be sure to select an equally harmonious set of contrasting colors for the text in each set of elements alse. Actually, all you really need to do is to make sure the color differences are easy to see and that the text remains easy to read. Be sure the three colors are clearly different from the htmb/body background color for the page.

Create background gradients for headings and paragraphs.

This part of the assignment is an exercise in working with images and opacity. There are several programs you could use to complete this part of the assignment, such as InkScape, Fireworks, and Photoshop together with its companion, ImageReady. InkScape is free software available from Inkscape.org; it is already installed on the computers in the lab. (The icon looks like a black blob, representing an inkblot.) Fireworks is part of Macromedia Studio, and is also installed on the computers in the lab. There are old versions of Photoshop and ImageReady installed in the lab, but we do not have current, licensed, versions installed yet.

Work through the Using Inkscape web page to create three different gradients, one for h1 elements, one with a different color for h2 elements, and a third one for paragraphs. Edit your screen.css style sheet so that all headings and paragraphs have their respective background images. Be sure to set them up so each image repeats in the y direction only. Set the background color of first level headings to something different from the page background and the gradient color so you can see the effect illustrated in the Using Inkscape introduction.

Submit the Assignment

When you have completed the assignment, send me an email message that says “CS-081 Assignment 3” in the subject line and that contains your real name and account name in the message body. I will get a copy of your work from maple to look at.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-081 Assignment 4

Introduction

This assignment is an exercise in using Javascript to alter the presentation of a web page interactively. The goal is for you to become familiar with Javascript, the DOM tree, and CSS all at the same time. Consider it an experimental approach!

If you have not done so, read the Javascript Tutorial assigned previously. We still haven’t covered forms yet, so you can skip that part of the tutorial. But you will need to work with events in this assignment, so you will need to understand that part as you go through this assignment.

Procedure

Create a new web page for this assignment and add a link to it from your home page.

Use your XHTML template to create a new web page and save it as a file named Assignment_04.xhtml. Change the title and h1 element to “Javascript Example,” and change the script in the head of the document from Template.js to Assignment_04.js. Save your new web page in your document root directory. Edit your index.xhtml file to add an unordered list in the header div just under the h1 element. But one item in the list, a link to Assignment_04.xhtml. Use “Javascript Example” as the content of the link. View your web site in the browser, and verify that the link is in place and that clicking on it it takes you to your new web page.

Add Javascript code to display four alert messages.

Ultimately, all Javascript code will be contained in Assignment_04.js, but for this part of the assignment, add additional script tags, one in the document head, and one in the document body. First add a few Lorem Ipsum paragraphs to the content part of the web page. Put one script tag in the head of the document, and the second one between the first and second paragraphs. Put the message, “Alert 1” in an alert() statement in the first one, and the message “Alert 2” in an alert() statement in the second one.

Create the Assignment_04.js file and save it inside your scripts directory. Put a third alert statement in the script file, and test that the three alert messages show up in the expected order.

Display the number of paragraphs as the page loads and when loading is complete.

Modify the three alert messages so they show the number of paragraph elements in the document as they execute. Add a fourth alert() statement that displays the number of paragraphs in the document after the DOM tree has been built.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-081 Assignment 5

Introduction

For this assignment you are to write a JavaScript event handler that changes the style of a table so that alternate rows have a different background color. I am providing a web page that creates tables with varying numbers of rows dynamically for your event handler to operate on.

Procedure

Set up the Contours web page in your own web site and test it.

I have a web page that calculates contour intervals at http://babbage.cs.qc.edu/Contours. Visit that page and make sure you understand what it does. I am providing you with a zip file that contains index.xhtml, css/style-screen.css and scripts/contours.js: Assignment_05.zip. Do not unzip this file directly into your web site, as it would overwrite your index page and stylesheet. Instead, unzip the contents to some other directory, such as your Desktop. Then rename index.xhtml to Assignment_05.xhtml and move it to your web site. Use Dreamweaver’s code editor to merge (copy and paste) the parts of my style-screen.css that you want to use into your own screen.css, and move contours.js into your scripts directory. Finally, create a link to Assignment_05.xhtml in the unordered list you added to your index page in Assignment 4, and verify that the page works from within your web site.

Add a second script file containing a JavaScript event handler.

At this point, Assignment_05.xhtml should be in your web site’s document root, and contours.js should be in your scripts directory. Add another script file, named assignment_05.js, to the script directory, and use a second script tag in the head of Assignment_05.xhtml to link to it. This second script tag must come after the tag for contours.js because it creates a variable in an object (ContourTable ) that doesn’t exist until the browser has processed contours.js. Put the following code in the new script file, and verify that it is executed whenever a new table is displayed:

ContourTable.notifyOnChange = function(theTable) { alert(theTable); }

Make the following changes so that this code is your “own” before proceding. Note that these changes will require you to edit parts of both contours.js and assignment_05.js.

Change the name of the event to DynamicTable.changeStyle
Change the name of the formal parameter in the event handler to aTable.

Be sure the page still works correctly before proceeding.

Code the event handler so that alternate rows of the table have different backgrounds.

There are three ground rules for doing this step. The first is that you are not allowed to change the XHTML file that I provided, nor are you to change the style sheet to add this effect. Second, except for the changes you had to make to contours.js in the previous step, you are to make no further changes to that file either. Finally, make sure your event handler changes only the data table; there is another table in the page that must not be changed.

If you want to make your code easier, you may assume that all rows are created with a white background, so you don’t have to change the ones that are already white.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .